<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Jervis Hollis speech the 26 of Aprill 1641</title>
            <title>Speech the 26 of Aprill 1641</title>
            <author>Holles, Gervase, 1606-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E198_4</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50874292</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50874292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74709)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ;  35:E198[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Jervis Hollis speech the 26 of Aprill 1641</title>
                  <title>Speech the 26 of Aprill 1641</title>
                  <author>Holles, Gervase, 1606-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In manuscript.</note>
                  <note>Addressed to Mr. Speaker.</note>
                  <note>The speech for which he was expelled from the House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:157479:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Jervis Hollis speech the 26 of Aprill <hi>1641.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have with much difficulty perswaded my selfe to offer any thing, my stockes little to this Reckoning, get since I haue adventured to rise, I shall take the Libertie with your Favours to deliver my selfe freelie; I have a blunt way in speaking my Hearte, it may be peradventure a follie in me, but it is a folly I love so well, I will not part with it:</p>
            <p>Sir, we are now vpon the 5<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Article of the Scots, which, as it was Empressed by a Noble L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. at the Conference, is a verie pregnant, and seeming Article, it hath produced manie other, and they such, as I must confesse and affirme, whatsoever Iucus or Artifice they be sleighted over with, I do not like their countenance: They may well be our younger brother Scotland, but like Jacob, they seeme to me, as if they had an aime to supplant vs, and take away our birthrighte.</p>
            <p>Sir, There is no man that hath a more charitable construction of Intentions then I had, whilest they made their addreſses in humble distance, as befilled Subjects to their Soveraigne; whilest they bounded their desires within the due limits of their Ancient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and seemed to wish nothing but the iust free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Subiects and Christians in their lawes and Consciences my heart went along with them,
<pb facs="tcp:157479:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
and I wished them satisfaction; But now S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. when I see them swell in their demands beyond all proportion, when I heard them indeare upon their first propositions, and require things vnfitt for a King to grant, and dishonourable for this Nation to suffer, I cannot but fixe a marke of danger vpon them, I feare we have nourished in our bosomes those that will sting vs to death.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here being interrupted, yet the House commanding him to goe on he saide as followeth.</head>
               <p>Sir, I am sorrie for this Interruption, much more sorry if I haue given a cause for it, for the clearenes of my owne thoughtes acquit me; I brought no Intentions here but such as were full of Fidelity and zeale for the service of this House, and my Countrey, and shall allwaies; And now if you please to command me to expresse my selfe like an Englishman, and an honest man, I shall proceede, otherwise I shall teſtify my obedience in my silence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Then he was comanded to proceede, which was as followeth.</head>
               <p>The miseries and calamities which this poore Kingdome hath thus long suffered; have hung like weights vpon my soule, and I have groaned vnder the oppression for it was a greate one; But these as they call
<pb facs="tcp:157479:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
them propositions, I must call them Comands and I feare they will prove so: They threaten yet more, it is to vnmam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vs quite and leaue vs in a Condition of all others most despiseable: For these appeare to me like the demands of Naash to the men of Jabesh pulling out our right eyes.</p>
               <p>Sir, our Ancestors have not beene acquainted with so much laments as to heare of such demands at diſtance, and it cannot but trouble me; that we should not onely meete them at the halfe way, but embrace the bearers.</p>
               <p>Sir, we are the offspring of those Ancestors, their bloud runnes in our vem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and I hope as yet is not all turn'd to water, there are the Spirits of life and activity in vs, and these will revive and Speake plaine English to vs what ever Dampe or Apoplexie this Spirit of slumber hath cast vpon vs, and I hope we shall either yet live with Honour, or take our Honourable Farewell, and so be honest and gallant men, betwixt these two there is not much difference. Therefore S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. my humble motion is this, That these Propositions may be committed to a Select Com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ittee to consider of, which carrie reason and modestie with them that they may be presented here, as filling to be granted, and that those which are of another Insinuation may be rejected: And if our firme peace may be had upon honest and honourable termes, I will cherish the thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:157479:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
of it, if not, there are but two wayes left worthy the Entertainemt of this Nation, that is, to stand or fall with honour.</p>
               <p>God I hope and our English vertues will secure the first, if otherwise, he is neither worthy of life, nor memory, that shall not bury himselfe in the ruines of his Countree.</p>
               <p>For this Speech by Consent of the Houſe he was expell'd the House for this Seſsion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:157479:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
